Ben Greenman
University of Utah
College of Engineering
Kahlert School of Computing
MEB 3252
50 Central Campus Drive
Salt Lake City, UT, 84112

benjamin.l.greenman@gmail.com cell: 781-924-9989

Research Interests _____

General interests: Language design issues regarding proofs, performance, and people. What guarantees do languages offer, how efficiently can they run, and to what extent do they help users meet their goals?

Keywords: Migratory typing, Language interoperability, Formal methods, Human factors

EDUCATION ___

| • Northeast | ern University | 2014 - 2020 |
|--|--------------------------------|-------------|
| Degree | Ph.D | |
| Area | Programming Languages | |
| Advisor | Matthias Felleisen | |
| Thesis | Deep and Shallow Types | |
| Cornell University | | 2013 - 2014 |
| Degree | Master of Engineering | |
| Major | Computer Science | |
| Advisor | Ross Tate | |
| • Cornell U | niversity | 2010 - 2013 |
| Degree | Bachelor of Science | |
| Major | Industrial and Labor Relations | |
| Minor | Computer Science | |
| • Hudson Valley Community College General studies, toward a guaranteed transfer to Cornell ILR | | 2009 - 2010 |

EMPLOYMENT ___

University of Utah
 Assistant Professor

 Brown University
 Postdoctoral Researcher, CIFellows 2020
 Mentor Shriram Krishnamurthi

| Knightsbridge Park Consultant, Web Scraping | 2017 | |
|---|-------------------|--|
| Cornell University Research Assistant | 2012 - 2014 | |
| • Rentenna Inc. Software Engineering Intern | 2012 - 2014 | |
| Teaching | | |
| • CS 5110/6110: Software Verification Instructor, 22 students | 2024 | |
| • CS 3520/6520: Programming Languages Co-Instructor with Matthew Flatt, 159 students | 2023 | |
| • Topics in PL and Systems: Tables and Humans Organizer | 2021 | |
| • Software Development Teaching Assistant | 2018, 2020 | |
| • Fundamentals I Teaching Assistant | 2016 | |
| Object-Oriented Design Teaching Assistant | 2016 | |
| • Functional Programming and Data Structures Teaching Assistant | 2012 - 2014 | |
| STUDENTS SUPERVISED | | |
| Mrigank Pawagi Undergraduate researcher, via OSRE 2024 | 2024 – ongoing | |
| • Hanwen Guo Ph.D., University of Utah | 2024 – ongoing | |
| Dominic Kennedy Ph.D., University of Utah | 2024 – ongoing | |
| Dibri Nsofor Ph.D., University of Utah | 2023 – ongoing | |
| Ashton Wiersdorf Ph.D., University of Utah | 2022 – ongoing | |
| Suyasha Bobhate M.S, University of Utah | 2023 - 2024 | |

| Sara Nurollahian Ph.D., University of Utah [Committee Member. Advisor: Eliane Wiese] | 2024 – ongoing |
|--|------------------------|
| Vivaan Rajesh Hillcrest High School, | 2023 – ongoing |
| • Siddhartha Prasad Ph.D., Brown University | 2022 – ongoing |
| Rob Durst Independent Researcher, | 2023 - 2023 |
| Caspar Popova Independent Researcher, | 2023 - 2023 |
| Aniket Karna M.S., University of Utah | 2023 - 2023 |
| Taylor Allred M.S., University of Utah | 2022 - 2023 |
| • Qianfan Chen Sc.B. with Honors [thesis], Brown University | 2021 - 2022 |
| • Kuang-Chen Lu Ph.D., Brown University | 2021 - 2022 |
| Milo Davis B.S., Northeastern University | 2017 |
| • Zeina Migeed B.S., Northeastern University | 2016 – 2017 |
| Awards | |
| Open Source Research Experience: Static Python Perf role: Mentor; funding via NSF 2024 Summer of Reproducibility PI Cormac Flanagan, Co-PI Stephanie Lieggi, Former PI Carlos Maltzahn | 2024 |
| • NSF SHF: Small: Little Tricky Logics role: Postdoc; PI Shriram Krishnamurthi, Co-PIs: Tim Nelson, Rob Lewis, and | 2023 I Milda Zizyte |
| CRA/CCC/NSF CI Fellowship | 2021 - 2023 |
| • SIGPLAN Student Scholarship: 50 Years of the ACM A.M. Turing Award | 2017 |
| Northeastern CCIS Graduate Community Service Award | 2016 |
| Cornell CS Teaching Award | 2014 |
| Cornell CS Teaching Award | 2013 |

Professional Service

• NSF Panel Reviewer 2024

• Teaching Area Coordinator: Programming Languages and Web 2024

• K-12 Outreach Planning Committee 2023 – 2024

• Co-Chair of Artifact Evaluation Committee & ERC OOPSLA 2023, 2022

• Program Committee SOAP 2024

TFP 2023 HATRA 2023, 2022

DLS 2022

ICFP 2021, PLDI 2021

• Reviewer JuliaCon 2024
ACM TOPLAS 2023

JFP 2024, 2023, 2020, 2019

• External Review Committee ESOP 2023, ICFP 2023

• Artifact Evaluation Committee ECOOP 2017, OOPSLA 2017, 2016

• Session Chair OOPSLA 2023, NJPLS 2023, ICFP 2021,

Publications —

Journal

• Ben Greenman, Christos Dimoulas, and Matthias Felleisen.

Typed–Untyped Interactions: A Comparative Analysis

TOPLAS 2023

Ben Greenman, Asumu Takikawa, Max S. New, Daniel Feltey, Robert Bruce Findler,
Jan Vitek, and Matthias Felleisen.

How to Evaluate the Performance of Gradual Type Systems

Conference, Symposium, and Hybrid Conference / Journal

• Ashton Wiersdorf, Stephen Chang, Matthias Felleisen, and Ben Greenman

ECOOP 2024

Type Tailoring

- Ben Greenman, Siddhartha Prasad, Antonio Di Stasio, Shufang Zhu,
 Giuseppe De Giacomo, Shriram Krishnamurthi, Marco Montali, Tim Nelson, and Milda Zizyte
 Misconceptions in Finite-Trace and Infinite-Trace Linear Temporal Logic
- Tim Nelson, Ben Greenman, Siddhartha Prasad, Tristan Dyer, Ethan Bove, OOPSLA 2024
 Qianfan Chen, Charles Cutting, Thomas Del Vecchio, Sidney LeVine, Julianne Rudner,
 Ben Ryjikov, Alexander Varga, Andrew Wagner, Luke West, and Shriram Krishnamurthi
 Forge: A Tool and Language for Teaching Formal Methods

- Ben Greenman, Alan Jeffrey, Shriram Krishnamurthi, and Mitesh Shah Programming 8.3, 2024 Privacy-Respecting Type Error Telemetry at Scale
- Siddhartha Prasad, Ben Greenman, Tim Nelson, and Shriram Krishnamurthi Programming 8.2, 2024 Conceptual Mutation Testing for Student Programming Misconceptions
- Siddhartha Prasad, Ben Greenman, Tim Nelson, and Shriram Krishnamurthi CompEd 2023 Generating Programs Trivially: Student Use of Large Language Models
- Ben Greenman, Matthias Felleisen, and Christos Dimoulas

 Mow Profilers Can Help Navigate Type Migration

 OOPSLA 2023
- Matthew Flatt, Taylor Allred, Nia Angle, Stephen De Gabrielle, Robert Bruce Finder, OOPSLA 2023 Jack Firth, Kiran Gopinathan, Ben Greenman, Siddhartha Kasivajhula, Alex Knauth, Jay McCarthy, Sam Phillips, Sorawee Porncharoenwase, Jens Axel Søgaard, and Sam Tobin-Hochstadt Rhombus: A New Spin on Macros Without All The Parentheses
- Lukas Lazarek, Ben Greenman, Matthias Felleisen, and Christos Dimoulas

 How to Evaluate Blame for Gradual Types, Part 2
- Ben Greenman ACM REP 2023

 GTP Benchmarks for Gradual Typing Performance
- Ben Greenman, Sam Saarinen, Tim Nelson, and Shriram Krishnamurthi Programming 7.2, 2023 Little Tricky Logic: Misconceptions in the Understanding of LTL
- Kuang-Chen Lu, Ben Greenman, Carl Meyer, Dino Viehland,
 Aniket Panse, and Shriram Krishnamurthi
 Gradual Soundness: Lessons from Static Python
- Siddhartha Prasad, Ben Greenman, Tim Nelson, John Wrenn, and Shriram Krishnamurthi
 Making Hay from Wheats: A Classsourcing Method to Identify Misconceptions
- Ben Greenman PLDI 2022 Deep and Shallow Types for Gradual Languages
- Ben Greenman, Lukas Lazarek, Christos Dimoulas, and Matthias Felleisen Programming 6.2, 2022 A Transient Semantics for Typed Racket
- Kuang-Chen Lu, Ben Greenman, and Shriram Krishnamurthi Programming 6.1, 2022 Types for Tables: A Language Design Benchmark
- Lukas Lazarek, Ben Greenman, Matthias Felleisen, and Christos Dimoulas
 ICFP 2021
 How to Evaluate Blame for Gradual Types
- Ben Greenman, Matthias Felleisen, and Christos Dimoulas

 Complete Monitors for Gradual Types
- Preston Tunnell Wilson, Ben Greenman, Justin Pombrio, Shriram Krishnamurthi.
 DLS 2018
 The Behavior of Gradual Types: A User Study

| • Daniel Feltey, Ben Greenman, Christophe Scholliers, Robert Bruce Findler, and Vincent St. Amour. Collapsible Contracts: Fixing a Pathology of Gradual Typing | OOPSLA 2018 |
|--|---------------|
| • Ben Greenman, Matthias Felleisen. A Spectrum of Type Soundness and Performance | ICFP 2018 |
| Ben Greenman, Zeina Migeed. On the Cost of Type-Tag Soundness | PEPM 2018 |
| • Sam Tobin-Hochstadt, Matthias Felleisen, Robert Bruce Findler, Matthew Flatt, Ben Greenman, Andrew M. Kent, Vincent St-Amour, T. Stephen Strickland, and Asumu Takikawa. Migratory Typing: 10 Years Later | SNAPL 2017 |
| • Stephen Chang, Ben Greenman, and Alex Knauth. Type Systems as Macros | POPL 2017 |
| Asumu Takikawa, Daniel Feltey, Ben Greenman, Max S. New, Jan Vitek, and Matthias Felleisen. Is Sound Gradual Typing Dead? | POPL 2016 |
| • Ben Greenman, Fabian Muehlboeck, and Ross Tate. Getting F-Bounded Polymorphism into Shape | PLDI 2014 |
| Workshop | |
| • Taylor Allred, Xinyi Li, Ashton Wiersdorf, Ben Greenman, and Ganesh Gopalakrishnan FlowFPX: Nimble Tools for Debugging Floating-Point Exceptions | JuliaCon 2023 |
| Asumu Takikawa, Daniel Feltey, Ben Greenman, Max S. New, Jan Vitek, and Matthias Felleisen. Position Paper: Performance Evaluation for Gradual Typing | STOP 2015 |
| Invited Talks | |
| • PLT @ Northwestern University Teaching Formal Methods with Forge | 2024 |
| • IETF 120: Usable Formal Methods Research Group Forge: Usable Model-Finding | 2024 |
| BYU Grad Seminar How Profilers Can Help Navigate Type Migration | 2023 |
| • TLf@AAAI-SSS'23 Towards LTLf Misconceptions | 2023 |
| • VardiFest, NJPLS Little Tricky Logic: Misconceptions in the Understanding of LTL | 2022 |

| • Racket Con Shallow Typed Racket Shallow and Optional Types for Typed Ra | 2020, 2022 acket |
|---|---|
| • Boston University POPV Seminar Complete Monitoring for Gradual Types | 2020 |
| GRACE Workshop Three Approaches to Gradual Typing | 2018 |
| Volunteering | |
| Price College Exploring Engineering Su | mmer Camp Summer 2024 |
| • El Turco: Human–Al dialogue Programmer | 2023 - 2024 |
| • Bootstrap Professional Development Teaching Assistant | Summer 2021 |
| Housing Chair | SPLASH 2018 |
| • Northeastern CCIS Hiring Committee Student Representative | Spring 2018 |
| • PRL Offsite Organizer | Fall 2019 |
| • Each One Teach One AP Java Tutor | Fall 2015 |
| • Student Volunteer | OOPSLA 2019; Turing Celebration 2017; POPL 2016, 2018; PLDI 2016; ICFP 2015, 2018; ECOOP 2015, 2016 |
| • Ithaca Media Arts Teacher, LEGO Mindstorms Camp | Summer 2012 |
| • Cornell Math Explorers Module Designer | Winter 2011 |
| Professional Memberships | |
| • IEEE | 2023 – ongoing |
| • IEEE Computer Society | 2023 – ongoing |
| • ACM | 2023 – ongoing |
| • ACM SIGPLAN | 2016 – ongoing |

BIOGRAPHY

Ben Greenman is an assistant professor in the Kahlert School of Computing at the University of Utah. He earned his Ph.D. from Northeastern University in 2020 and was a CIFellows 2020 postdoc at Brown University. His research focus is the science of language design. His team develops methods to measure performance, prove guarantees, and understand human factors for languages and systems.